Sushovan Majhi

Assistant Professor, Data Science Program, George Washington University Samson Hall 302, George Washington University, Washington, D.C., USA s.majhi[AT]gwu.edu | Homepage | GitHub | Google Scholar | LinkedIn

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Algebraic and Applied Topology, Discrete and Computational Geometry, Topological Data Analysis (TDA), Pattern and Shape Matching, Statistical Finance.

My research primarily revolves around the interface of *computer science*, *mathematics*, and the mathematical foundations of *data science*. More specifically, I am motivated to develop provable inference techniques for data science that are inspired by topology and geometry. I also keep a keen interest in applying TDA to fascinating, real-world problems arising in fields, like biology, medicine, genetics, finance, and dynamical systems.

WORK EXPERIENCE

• Assistant Professor

Data Science Program, George Washington University, Washington D.C., USA

August 2024–current

• Visiting Assistant Professor

August 2023-May 2023

Data Science Program, George Washington University, Washington D.C., USA

Role: Teaching data science and computer science courses to graduate students in the Data Science Program.

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

January 2021-July 2023

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

Role: The responsibilities included conducting research broadly in data science, forging new research collaborations, organizing research webinar series.

EDUCATION

• Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, USA.

August 2014-December 2020

Advisor: Prof. Carola Wenk

Courses: computational geometry, computational topology, topological data analysis, differential geometry, differentiable manifolds, algorithms, data structures, computational complexity, applied mathematics, and scientific computing.

• Master of Science in Mathematics

August 2009-May 2012

Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Bangalore, India

Courses: ordinary and partial differential equations, probability theory, complex analysis, functional analysis, numerical linear algebra, measure theory, mechanics.

• Bachelor of Science in Mathematics (Hons.)

July 2006-May 2009

Ramakrishna Mission Vidyamandira, Calcutta University, West Bengal, India

Courses: calculus, real analysis, linear algebra, numerical analysis, game theory, statistics, physics.

GRADUATE STUDENT ADVISEES

• Khush Shah and Shikha Kumari, current data science masters students, George Washington University,

August 2023-current

Project Title: Matching geometric graphs

• Anish Rai, PhD student at

August 2022-August 2024

National Institute of Technology, Sikkim, India

Project Title: Prediction of stock market crashes using topological data analysis

PREPRINTS

- 4. Rafal Komendarczyk **SM**, Will Tran. Topological Stability and Latschev-type Reconstruction Theorems for CAT(κ) Spaces, 29 pages, June 2024. Available at: arXiv:2406.04259 [math.AT]
- 3. Anish Rai, Buddha Nath Sharma, Salam Rabindrajit Luwang, Md.Nurujjaman, **SM**. Identifying Extreme Events in the Stock Market: A Topological Data Analysis, 14 pages, June 2024. Available at: arXiv:2405.05642 [q-fin.ST]
 - Submitted to Chaos: An Interdisciplinary Journal of Nonlinear Science
- 2. Kundan Mukhia, Anish Rai, SR Luwang, Md Nurujjaman, **SM**, Chittaranjan Hens. Complex Network Analysis of Cryptocurrency Market During Crashes, 12 pages, May 2024. Available at: arXiv:2405.05642 [q-fin.ST]
 - Submitted to *Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications*
- 1. Henry Adams, Florian Frick, **SM**, Nichola McBride*. Hausdorff VS Gromov–Hausdorff Distances, 22 pages, Sep 2023. Available at: arXiv:2309.16648 [math.MG]
 - Submitted to Discrete and Computational Geometry

JOURNAL PAPERS

- 6. **SM**. Demystifying Latschev's theorem: Manifold Reconstruction from noisy data. *Discrete & Computational Geometry*, 2024. DOI: 10.1016/j.comgeo.2023.102056. 2024. Available at: arXiv:2305.17288[math.AT]
- 5. **SM** and Carola Wenk. Distance Measures for geometric graphs. *Computational Geometry: Theory and Applications*, 2023. DOI: 10.1016/j.comgeo.2023.102056. Also available at: arXiv:2209.12869[cs.CG]
- 4. **SM**. Vietoris–Rips complexes of metric spaces near a metric graph. *Journal of Applied and Computational Topology*, May 2023. DOI: 10.1007/s41468-023-00122-z
 Also available at: arXiv:2204.14234[math.AT]
- 3. **SM**, Jeffrey Vitter, and Carola Wenk. Approximating Gromov-Hausdorff distance in Euclidean space. *Computational Geometry: Theory and Applications*, 116:102034, 2024. DOI: 10.1016/j.comgeo.2023.102034. Also available at: arXiv:1912.13008[math.MG]
- 2. Anish Rai, Ajit Mahata, Md Nurujjaman, **SM**, and Kanish Debnath. A sentiment-based modeling and analysis of stock price during the COVID-19: U- and Swoosh-shaped recovery. *Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications*, 592:126810, 2022. DOI: 10.1016/j.physa.2021.126810
- 1. Brittany Terese Fasy, Rafal Komendarczyk, **SM**, and Carola Wenk. On the reconstruction of geodesic subspaces of \mathbb{R}^N . *International Journal of Computational Geometry & Applications*, 32(1):91–117, 2022. DOI: 10.1142/S0218195922500066. Also available at: arXiv:1810.10144[math.AT]

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PAPERS

- 3. **SM**. Demystifying Latschev's theorem: Manifold Reconstruction from noisy data. In Proceedings of the *40th International Symposium on Computational Geometry (SoCG)*, Athens, Greece, June 11–14, 2024. Available at: https://doi.org/10.4230/LIPIcs.SoCG.2024.73
- 2. Erin Chambers, Brittany Fasy, Benjamin Holmgren*, **SM**, and Carola Wenk. Metric and path-connectedness properties of the Frěchet distance for paths and graphs. In Proceedings of the *34th Canadian Conference on Computational Geometry (CCCG)*, 2023. Available at: arXiv:2308.00900[cs.CG]

^{*} Undergraduate student at the time of research or submission

1. **SM**. Graph mover's distance: An efficiently computable distance measure for geometric graphs. In Proceedings of the *34th Canadian Conference on Computational Geometry (CCCG)*, 2023. Available at: arXiv:2306.02133[cs.CG]

WORKSHOP CONTRIBUTIONS

- 4. E. Chambers, B. Fasy, B. Holmgren*, **SM**, and C. Wenk. Path-Connectivity of Fréchet Spaces of Graphs. Computational Geometry: Young Researchers Forum, 2022
- 3. **SM** and Carola Wenk. Distance Measures for Geometric Graphs, At *Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry (FWCG)*, 2022
- 2. Brittany Terese Fasy, **SM** and Carola Wenk. Threshold-based graph reconstruction using discrete Morse theory. In *Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry (FWCG)*, 2018. Abstract available at: Link
- 1. Brittany Terese Fasy, Rafal Komendaczyk, SM, and Carola Wenk. Topological reconstruction of metric graphs in \mathbb{R}^N . At Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry (FWCG), 2017. Abstract available at: Link

AWARDS, SCHOLARSHIPS, RECOGNITION

• NSF: Mathematical & Physical Sciences (MPS), Declined

Title: Geometric Approach to the Shape Reconstruction from Noisy Data

Role: co-PI

PI: Rafal Komendarczyk, Tulane University, New Orleans.

- Travel Grant, University of California, Berkeley
- UGC-CSIR NET Research Fellowship, India, June 2012
- TIFR Junior Research Fellowship for pursuing Integrated PhD studies at TIFR-CAM, Bangalore, India. August 2009.
- Secured grade "A" in SCIENCE TALENT SEARCH EXAMINATION conducted by JATIYA VIJNAN PARISAD and INDIAN SCIENCE CONGRESS ASSOCIATION

GRADUATE TEACHING

• Linear Algebra for Data Science

Summer 2024

Data Science Program, George Washington University, USA

Topics: linear algebra foundations, Gaussian elimination, pivoting techniques for stability, LU decomposition, eigenvalues and eigenvectors, solving linear systems using iterative methods, projections and linear regression, SVD and applications.

• Algorithm Design (DATS 6001)

Spring 2024

Data Science Program, George Washington University, USA

Topics: basics of computational complexity, data structures (array, stack, queue, tree, etc), algorithms (search, sort, etc), and programming paradigms like dynamic and greedy algorithms.

• Topological Data Analysis (CS)

Fall 2023

National Institute of Technology, Sikkim, India

Topics: topological spaces, metric spaces and their examples, simplicial complexes, homology in $\mathbb{Z}/2$ coeff, persistent homology, bottleneck and Wasserstein distance, and non-linear time-series analysis using TDA.

^{*} Undergraduate student at the time of research or submission Last updated: June 9, 2024

• Computer Science Foundations (DATS 6450)

Fall 2023

Data Science Program, George Washington University, USA *Topics:* computer design, programming in Python, object-oriented programming

• Introduction to Data Mining (DATS 6103)

Fall 2023, Spring 2024

Data Science Program, George Washington University, USA

Topics: data wrangling, linear and logistic regression, classification, clustering, data visualization, support vector machines, machine learning algorithms.

• Statistics for Data Science (MIDS 203)

August 2020-July 2023

School of Information, University of California, Berkeley, USA

Topics: probability theory, sampling distributions, estimators and convergence theorems, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, and regression.

• Linear Algebra, Complex Analysis

January 2013-June 2013

Christ University and Scimetric Pvt Ltd, Bangalore, India

• Analysis, Linear Algebra, Complex Analysis

November 2011-July 2012

GATE-IIT Coaching Institute, JP Nagar, Bangalore, India Graduate level, for competitive national exams, e.g., National Eligibility Test

Analysis and Linear Algebra

February 2012-July 2012

MES College, Department of Mathematics, Malleswaram, Bangalore, India

UNDERGRADUATE TEACHING

• Undergraduate Statistics for Business Students (MATH 1140)

Summer 2019

Tulane University, USA

Topics: sampling methods, descriptive statistics, probability theory, random variables, limit theorems, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, and linear regression.

OTHER TEACHING

• Teaching Assistant
Tulane University, USA

Fall 2014-Spring 2017

ACADEMIC SERVICES

- I have been a reviewer for Journal of Foundations of Data Science.
- I have been a reviewer for Journal of Combinatorial Optimization.
- I have been a reviewer for conferences, like the International Symposium on Computational Geometry, International Symposium on Spatial and Temporal Databases, European Workshop on Computational Geometry, ACM International Conference on Advances in Geographic Information Systems, WADS Algorithms and Data Structures Symposium.
- I organized SIAM Graduate Student Chapters at Tulane University.
- I have been organizing a data science webinar series at the University of California, Berkeley.

COMPUTATIONAL SKILLS

Java, C, R, Python, Ruby, JavaScript, SQL, Bash.

SOFTWARE PROJECTS

• Simplicial Complexes in JS

GitHub

JavaScript implementation of some of the widely used computations on simplicial complexes. The library also implements the Smith Normal Form in order to compute the homology groups of an abstract complex.

• Shape Reconstruction Visualization

WebApp GitHub

To complement my PhD research, I implemented my topological reconstruction algorithm for planar metric graphs in this library. The library is written in JavaScript and made available to users as a web-app. *Skills*: JavaScript, HTML, CSS.

ENTREPRENEURIAL EXPERIENCE

Scimetric Edulabs Private Limited

December 2012-April 2017

Bangalore, India

Role: co-founder and director

In this start-up venture, our objective was to motivate and train students in higher education. We won the franchise to work with several private colleges in India. We coached science students for standardized entrance tests for PhD and academic jobs. The company employed 6 trainers.

INVITED TALKS AND ACCEPTED ABSTRACTS

• Title: Demystifying Latschev's Theorem Symposium on Computational Geometry, Athens, Greece

June 14, 2024

• **Title:** Demystifying Latschev's Theorem Montana State University

March 28, 2024

• Title: Demystifying Latschev's Theorem

August 23, 2023

Applied Algebraic Topology Research Network (AATRN)

Available on: YouTube

• Title: Graph Mover's Distance

August 2-4, 2023

The 34th Canadian Conference on Computational Geometry, Montreal, Canada

Available on: Google Drive

Title: Similarity Measures for Geometric Graphs
 The 30th Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry
 North Carolina State University, USA

October 14-15, 2022

• **Title:** Topological Methods in the Reconstruction and Comparison of Shapes Mathematics Department, ICFAI University, Tripura, India

February, 2022

• Title: A Taste of Topological Data Analysis (TDA): Reconstruction of Shapes Department of Mathematics, Hunter College, NY, USA

September, 2021

 Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry Queens College, New York, USA October, 2018

 Fall Workshop on Computational Geometry SUNY (Stony Brook), New York, USA November, 2017

Новву

In my spare time, I write tutorials on *random* topics in order to make mathematics and statistics a little more interactive; they can be found here: https://www.smajhi.com/tutorials. I also enjoy playing the piano and classical guitar.